CHAPTER 24 LET THEM LAUGH" The secret garden was not the only
one dickan worked in around the cottage on the mo there was a piece of ground
enclosed by a low wall of rough stones. Early in the morning and late in
the fading twilight and on all the days Colin and Mary did not see him dickan
worked there planting or tending potatoes and cabbages, turnips and carrots and herbs for his
mother. In the company of his "creatures" he did wonders there and was
never tired of doing them, it seemed.
While he dug or weeded he whistled or sang bits of Yorkshire Moore songs or
talked to suot or Captain or the brothers and sisters he had taught to help
him. "We'd never get on as comfortable as we do," Mrs sby said, "if it wasn't for
dickens's garden anything will grow for him. His Tes and cabbages is twice the
size of of anyone else's and they've got a flavor with them as nobody's
has." When she found a moment to spare she liked to go out and talk to
him. After supper there was still a long clear twilight to work in and that was
her quiet time. She could sit upon the low rough wall and look on and hear
stories of the day. She loved this time. There were not only vegetables in
this garden. Dickon had bought pennies packages of flower seeds now and then
and sewn bright sweet scented things among gooseberry bushes and even
cabbages and he grew borders of Minette and pinks and pansies and things whose
seeds he could save year after year or whose roots would bloom each spring and
spread in time into fine clumps. The low wall was one of the prettiest things in
Yorkshire because he had tucked Morland Fox Glove and ferns and Rock and hedge
flowers into every crevice until only here and there glimpses of the stones were to be
seen. "All a chap's got to do to make him thrive, mother," he would say, "is to be
friends with them for sure. They're just like the creatures.' If they're thirsty give them a
drink and if they're hungry give them a bit of food. They want to live same as we
do. If they died I should feel as if I'd been a bad lad and somehow treated them
heartless." It was in these twilight hours that Mrs sby heard of all that happened
at mwe Manor. At first she was only told that me Collin had taken a fancy to
going out into the grounds with Miss Mary and that it was doing him good. But
it was not long before it was agreed between the two children that Dick's
mother might "come into the secret." Somehow it was not doubted that she was "safe for
sure." So one beautiful still evening Dickon told the whole story, with all the
thrilling details of the buried key and the robin and the gray haze which had
seemed like deadness and the secret Mistress Mary had planned never to
reveal. The coming of Dickon and how it had been told to him, the doubt of me
Collin and the final drama of his inter uction to the hidden domain, combined
with the incident of Ben Weatherstaff's angry face peering over the wall and me
Collin's sudden indignant strength, made Mrs sau's Nic looking face quite change color several
times. "My word!" she said. "It was a good thing that little lass came to the Manor.
It's been the making of her and the saving of him standing on his feet and
us all thinking he was a poor half-witted lad with not a straight bone
in him." She asked a great many questions and her blue eyes were full of deep
thinking. "What do they make of it at the Manor— —him being so well and cheerful and
never complaining she inquired. "They don't know what to make of it," answered
Dickon. "Every day as comes round his face looks different. It's filling out and
doesn't look so sharp and the waxy color is going But he has to do his bitter
complaining with a highly entertained grin. "What for in Mercy's name?" asked Mrs
saby Dickon chuckled. "He does it to keep them from guessing what's happened. If
the doctor knew he'd found out he could stand on his feet he'd likely write and
tell Mr Craven Mr Collins saving the secret to tell himself. He's going to
practices Magic on his legs every day till his father comes back and then he's
going to march into his room and show him he's as straight as other lads. But
him and Miss Mary thinks it's best planed to do a bit of groaning and
fretting now and then to throw folk off the scent." Mrs sby was laughing a low
comfortable laugh long before he had finished his last sentence e she said,
"that pair's enjoying their themselves I'll warrant. They'll get a good bit of
play acting out of it and there's nothing children likes as much as play
acting Let's hear what they do dick and lad Dickens stopped weeding and sat up
on his heels to tell her. His eyes were twinkling with
fun Mr Collin is carried down to his chair every time he goes out," he
explained and he flies out at JN the footman, for not carrying him careful
enough. He makes himself as helpless looking as he can and never lifts his
head until we're out a sight of the house and he grunts and frets a good bit
when he's being settled into his chair.
Him and and Miss Mary's both got to enjoy in it and when he groans and
complains she'll say, 'Poor Colin! Does it hurt you so much? Are you so weak as that,
poor Colin?'— ?'—but the trouble is that sometimes they can scarce keep from bursting out
laughing When we get safe into the garden they laugh till they've no breath
left to laugh with and they have to stuff their faces into M Collins's
cushions to keep the gardeners from hearing if any of them's
about the more they laugh the better for him said Mrs saby still laughing herself.
"Good healthy child laughing's better than pills any day of the year. That pair
will plump up for sure." "They are Plumping up," said Dickon.
"They're that hungry they don't know how to get enough to eat without making talk
Mr Collin says if he keeps sending for more food they won't believe he's an
invalid at all. Miss Mary says she'll let him eat her share, but he says that if
she goes hungry she'll get thin and they men both get fat at
once." Mrs sby laughed so heartily at the revelation of this difficulty, that she
quite rocked backward and forward in her blue cloak, and Dicken laughed with
her. "I'll tell thee what, lad," Mrs saby said when she could speak. "I've thought
of a way to help him When that goes to him in the mornings there she'll take a
pale of good new milk and I'll bake him a crusty cottage loaf or some buns with
currents in them same as you children like nothing so good as fresh milk and
bread. Then they could take off the edge of their hunger while they were in their
garden and the fine food they get indoors had polish off the
corners a mother!" said Dickon admiringly, "what a wonder Thou art Thou
always sees a way out of things. They was quite in a PO the yesterday. They didn't
see how they was to manage without ordering up more food— —they felt that empty
inside." "They're two young ons growing fast and health's coming back to both of
them Children like that feels like young wolves and Foods flesh and blood to them said Mrs
sby Then she smiled Dickon's own curving smile. "Eh! but they're enjoying their
themselves for sure," she said. She was quite right, the comfortable wonderful
mother creature— —and she had never been more so than when she said their "play
actin'" would be their joy. Colin and Mary found it one of their most thrilling sources of
entertainment. The idea of protecting themselves from suspicion had been
unconsciously suggested to them first by the puzzled nurse and then by Dr. Craven
himself. "Your appetite is improving very much, Master Colin," the had said one day.
"You used to eat nothing, and so many things disagreed with you." "Nothing
disagrees with me now," replied Colin, and then seeing the nurse looking at him
curiously he suddenly remembered that perhaps he ought not to appear too well just
yet. "At least things don't so often disagree with me. It's the fresh
air." "Perhaps it is," said the nurse, still looking at him with a mystified expression.
"But I must talk to Dr. Craven about it." "How she stared at you!" said Mary when
she went away. "As if she thought there must be something to find
out." "I won't have her finding out things," said Colin. "No one must begin to find out
yet." When Dr. Craven came that morning he seemed puzzled, also. He asked a number of
questions, to Colin's great annoyance.
"You stay out in the garden a great deal," he suggested. "Where do you go?" Colin put
on his favorite air of dignified indifference to opinion. "I will not let anyone know where
I go," he answered. "I go to a place I like
everyone has orders to keep out of the way. I won't be watched and stared at. You know
that!" "You seem to be out all day but I do
not think it has done you harm— —I do not think so. The nurse says that you eat
much more than you have ever done before." "Perhaps," said Colin, prompted by a sudden
inspiration, "perhaps it is an unnatural appetite." "I do not think so, as your food
seems to agree with you," said Dr. Craven.
"You are gaining flesh rapidly and your color is better." "Perhaps— —perhaps I am bloated and
feverish," said Colin, assuming a discouraging air of gloom. "People who are
not going to live are often— —different." Dr.
Craven shook his head. He was holding Colin's wrist and he pushed up his
sleeve and felt his arm. "You are not feverish," he said thoughtfully, "and such
fleshes you have gained is healthy. If we can keep this up, my boy, we need not talk
of dying. Your father will be very happy to hear of this remarkable
improvement." "I won't have him told!"
Colin broke forth fiercely. "It will only disappoint him if I get worse again— —and
I may get worse this very night. I might
have a raging fever. I feel as if I might be beginning to have one now. I won't
have letters written to my father— —I won't— —I won't! You are making me angry
and you know that is bad for me. I feel hot already. I hate being written about
and being talked over as much as I hate being stared at hush my boy," Dr. Craven
soothed him. "Nothing shall be written without your permission. You are too
sensitive about things. You must not undo the good which has been
done." He said no more about writing to Mr.
Craven and when he saw the nurse he privately warned her that such a
possibility must not be mentioned to the patient. "The boy is extraordinarily
better," he said. "His advance seems almost abnormal. But of course he is doing now
of his own free will what we could not make him do before. Still, he excites
himself very easily and nothing must be said to irritate
him." Mary and Colin were much alarmed and talked together anxiously. From this time
dated their plan of "play acting I may be obliged to have a tantrum," said Colin
regretfully. "I don't want to have one and I'm not miserable enough now to work
myself into a big one. Perhaps I couldn't have one at
all. That lump doesn't come in my throat now and I keep thinking of nice things
instead of horrible ones. But if they talk about writing to my father I shall
have to do something." He made up his mind to eat less, but unfortunately it was not
possible to carry out this brilliant idea when he wakened each morning with
an amazing appetite and the table near his sofa was set with a breakfast of
homemade bread and fresh butter snow white eggs, raspberry jam and clotted
cream. Mary always breakfasted with him and when they found themselves at the
table— —particularly if there were delicate slices of sizzling ham sending
forth tempting odors from under a hot silver cover— —they would look into each other's eyes in
desperation. "I think we shall have to eat it all this morning, Mary," Colin always
ended by saying.
"We can send away some of the lunch and a great deal of the dinner." But they never
found they could send away anything and the highly polished condition of the
empty plates return to the pantry awakened much comment. "I do wish," Colin would say
also, "I do wish the slices of ham were thicker, and one muffin each is not enough for
anyone It's enough for a person who is going to die," answered Mary when first
she heard this, "but it's not enough for a person who is going to
live. I sometimes feel as if I could eat three when those nice fresh heather and
gor smells from the mo come pouring in at the open window." The morning that
Dickon— —after they had been enjoying themselves in the garden for about 2
hours— —went behind a big rose bush and brought forth two tin pales and revealed
that one was full of rich new milk with cream on the top of it, and that the
other held Cottage made currant buns folded in a clean blue and white napkin,
buns so carefully tucked in that they were still hot, there was a riot of
surprised joyfulness. What a wonderful thing for Mrs saby to think of! What a
kind, clever woman she must be! How good the buns were! And what delicious fresh
milk! "Magic is in her just as it is in Dickon," said Colin. "It makes her think of
ways to do things— —nice things. She is a Magic person. Tell her we are grateful,
Dickon— —extremely grateful." He was given to using rather grown-up phrases at times. He enjoyed
them. He liked this so much that he improved upon it. "Tell her she has been
most bounous and our gratitude is extreme dream And then forgetting his
grandeur he fell to and stuffed himself with buns and drank milk out of the pale
in copious drafts in the manner of any hungry little boy who had been taking
unusual exercise and breathing in Morland air and whose breakfast was more
than 2 hours behind him. This was the beginning of many agreeable incidents of the same
kind. They actually awoke to the fact that as Mrs saby had 14 people to
provide food for she might not have enough to satisfy two extra appetites every
day. So they asked her to let them send some of their shillings to buy
things. Dickon made the stimulating discovery that in the wood in the park
outside the garden where Mary had first found him piping to the wild
creatures there was a deep little hollow where you could build a sort of tiny
oven with stones and roast potatoes and eggs in it. Roasted eggs were a
previously unknown luxury and very hot potatoes with salt and fresh butter in
them were fit for a woodland king— —besides being deliciously
satisfying. You could buy both potatoes and eggs and eat as many as you liked
without feeling as if you were taking food out of the mouths of 14
people. Every beautiful morning the Magic was worked by the my circle under the
Plum Tree which provided a canopy of thickening green leaves after its brief Blossom time was
ended. After the ceremony Colin always took his walking exercise and throughout
the day he exercised his newly found power at intervals. Each day he grew stronger and
could walk more steadily and cover more ground. And each day his belief in the
Magic grew stronger— —as well it might. He tried one experiment
after another as he felt himself gaining strength and it was Dickon who showed
him the best things of all. "Yesterday," he said one morning after an
absence, "I went to thit for mother and near the Blue Cow in I seed Bob harworth
He's the strongest chap on the mo He's the champion wrestler and he can jump
high than any other chap and throw the hammer farther. He's gone all the way to
Scotland for the sports some years. He's know me ever since I was a little one
and he's a friendly sort and I asked him some questions the gentry calls him a
athlete and I thought of thee Master Colin, and I says, 'How did thou make thy
muscles stick out that way, Bob? Did thou do anything extra to make thyself so
strong and he says 'Well, yes, lad, I did. A
strong man in a show that came to thit once showed me how to exercise my arms
and legs and every muscle in my body and I says, 'Could a delicate chap make
himself stronger with them Bob and he laughed and says, 'Art thou the delicate
chap and I says, 'No, but I knows a young gentleman that's getting well of a long
illness and I wish I knowed some of them tricks to tell him about.' I didn't say no
names and he didn't ask none. He's friendly same as I said head and he
stood up and showed me good natured like and I imitated what he did till I knowed
it by heart." Colin had been listening excitedly. "Can you show me?" he cried. "Will
you I to be sure," Dickon answered, getting up. "But he says th man do him gentle at
first and be careful not to tire thy C Rest in between times and take deep
breaths and don't overdo." "I'll be careful," said Colin. "Show
me! Show me! Dickon, you are the most Magic boy in the
world!" Dickon stood up on the grass and slowly went through a carefully
practical but simple series of muscle exercises. Colin watched them with
widening eyes. He could do a few while he was sitting
down. Presently he did a few gently while he stood upon his already steadied feet.
Mary began to do knew them also suot who was watching the performance, became much
disturbed and left his branch and hopped about restlessly because he could not do them
too. From that time the exercises were part of the day's duties as much as the Magic
was. It became possible for both Colin and Mary to do more of them each time
they tried, and such appetites were the results that but for the B
Dickon put down behind the bush each morning when he arrived they would have been
lost. But the little oven in the hollow and Mrs sau's bounties were so
satisfying that Mrs. Medlock and the nurse and Dr. Craven became mystified
again. You can trifle with your breakfast and seem to disdain your dinner if you
are full to the brim with roasted eggs and potatoes and richly frothed new milk
and oat cakes and buns and heather honey and clotted cream. "They
are eating next to nothing," said the nurse. "They'll die of starvation if they
can't be persuaded to take some nourishment. And yet see how they look."
"Look!" exclaimed Mrs. Medlock indignantly ah I'm moyed to death with
them. They're a pair of young Satans.
Bursting their jackets one day and the next turning up their noses at the best
meals could contempt them with. Not a mouthful of that lovely young fowl and
bread sauce did they set a fork into yesterday— —and the poor woman fair
invented a pudding for them— —and back it sent. She almost cried. She's afraid
she'll be blamed if they starve themselves into their graves." Dr. Craven came and looked at
Colin long and carefully. He wore an extremely worried expression when the nurse t with him and
showed him the almost untouched tray of breakfast she had saved for him to look
at— —but it was even more worried when he sat down by Colin's sofa and examined
him. He had been called to London on business and had not seen the boy for nearly 2
weeks. When young things begin to gain health they gain it rapidly. The wax and tinge had left
Colin's skin and a warm rose showed through it; his beautiful eyes were clear
and the hollows under them and in his cheeks and temples had filled out. His
once dark, heavy locks had begun to look as if they sprang healthily from his
forehead and were soft and warm with life. His lips were fuller and of a
normal color. In fact as an imitation of a boy who was a confirmed invalid he was
a disgraceful sight. Dr. Craven held his chin in in his hand and thought him over.
"I am sorry to hear that you do not eat anything he said. "That will not do. You
will lose all you have gained— —and you have gained amazingly. You ate so well a short time
ago." "I told you it was an unnatural appetite," answered Colin. Mary was sitting
on her stool nearby and she suddenly made a very queer sound which she tried
so violently to press that she ended by almost choking. "What is the matter?" said Dr.
Craven, turning to look at her. Mary became quite severe in her manner. "It was
something between a sneeze and a cough," she replied with reproachful dignity, "and
it got into my throat." "But" she said afterward to Colin, "I
couldn't stop myself. It just burst out because all at once I couldn't help
remembering that last big potato you weight and the way your mouth stretched
when you bit through that thick lovely crust with jam and clotted cream on
it." "Is there any way in which those children can get food
secretly?" Dr. Craven inquired of Mrs.
Medlock. "There's no way unless they dig it out of the earth or pick it off the
trees," Mrs. Medlock answered. "They stay out in the grounds
all day and see no one but each other.
And if they want anything different to eat from what's sent up to them they
need only ask for it." "Well," said Dr. Craven, "so long as going
without food agrees with them we need not disturb ourselves. The boy is a new
creature." "So is the girl," said Mrs. Medlock.
"She's begun to be downright pretty since she's filled out and lost her ugly
little sour look. Her hair's grown thick and healthy looking and she's got a
bright color. The glamest ill-natured little thing she used to be and now her
and Master Colin laughed together like a pair of crazy young ones. Perhaps they're
growing fat on that." "Perhaps they are," said Dr. Craven. "Let them
laugh." CHAPTER 25 THE CURTAIN And the